Guide to the New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection OH.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- New York City Immigrant Labor History Project, 593058
  - Harris, Shirley, 1973 April 11; 593161 (Box 85, Reel 820a - 820b, Box 1, Folder 39)
    This interview was conducted by Martin Lesser on April 11, 973 at an unknown location. The date and location of the interview are unknown. The interview covers Shirley Harris' childhood in Poland and Austria, her working life, and her family. Harris discusses her childhood in Poland and Austria; her religious upbringing; her experiences during World War I; and her family's immigration to Austria after an attack on their village by Russian troops. She discusses immigrating to the United States with her mother and two siblings and joining the workforce as soon as she came of age. She describes her first job in a dress factory working as a floor girl, sewing belts onto dresses by hand. She discusses learning to use a sewing machine and becoming a machine operator, which she preferred to sewing by hand. She discusses her membership in the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU) and differences in the ILGWU when she first joined and at the time of the interview. Other topics include her distrust of politicians, except for Franklin D. Roosevelt, whom she admired; the changing ethnic and racial demographics of the workforce of the garment industry; and her daughter.
    See also: Immigration, Migration, and First Impressions of New York, New York and the United States.
    World War, 1914-1918 |z Poland |v Personal narratives.
  - Heltzer, Fanny, Undated; 593240 (Box 95, Reel 900a - 900c, Box 96, Reel 900c, Box 1, Folder 40)
    Fanny Heltzer was born in Kiev, Russia in the late 1880s. She was one of five children. Her father worked as a merchant in Kiev and died when she was seven years old. After she was widowed, her mother ran a small restaurant to support her family. Heltzer attended school in Kiev until she was 15 years old, when she became a live-in apprentice to a furrier in Kiev. She immigrated to the United States in 1906 when she was 17 years old. She initially lived with her sister on Houston Street in Manhattan, New York before moving in with a friend in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. She attended a practical nursing class at Beth Israel Hospital in Manhattan from 1907 to 1908 and married in September 1909. She moved to Shelton, Connecticut during World War I; moved to Worcester, Massachusetts to accommodate her husband's business venture; and moved back to New York City in 1921 when that venture failed. They moved often, living in the Lower East Side, Hell's Kitchen, and Harlem neighborhoods of Manhattan before settling in the Bronx in 1927.
    Heltzer worked as a machine operator and finisher in various shops in the garment industry, making dresses, sweaters, bathing suits, and corsets. After working the garment industry, she worked as an unlicensed private nurse until her retirement in 1965. She was an active member of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union Local 55; the Workers' Unemployed Union, eventually serving as chairman of the Bronx locals; the Workmen's Circle, heading the Friendship Club; and the Socialist Party of America.
    This interview was conducted by Karen Kearns. The date and location of this interview are unknown. This interview covers Fanny Heltzer's childhood in Russia; her immigration to the United States (US) in 1906; and her work in the garment industry and as a private nurse in New York, New York. Heltzer begins the interview by describing her childhood in Kiev, noting that conversations regarding politics were forbidden in school; that she acquired her Socialist viewpoints from family and friends; and that she attended secret Socialist meetings. She recalls that her mother paid for her to be a live-in apprentice to a furrier in Kiev because her sister noted the high-paying opportunities in that industry in the US. She describes her mother sending Heltzer's oldest sister to the US in the hopes that she would eventually be able to send for the rest of the family. She explains that her brother was sent to Siberia due to his revolutionary activity and that their mother sent him to the United States in order to prevent his being arrested again. She notes that she immigrated soon after him in 1906, with their two remaining sisters following her.
    Heltzer explains that she initially lived with her sister on Houston Street in Manhattan but moved in with a friend because of her sister's overbearing rules. She explains that she acquired her first job in a ladies' shirtwaist shop through the recommendation of a friend, noting her initial fear of the speed and noise of the electric sewing machines; that the conditions of the shop were filthy; and that she quit because of the poor conditions and the long work week. She explains that her next jobs in Manhattan, in a dress shop and at the Nemo Corset Company, were better due to the cleaner conditions in the shops. She notes that employees at the Nemo Corset Company were afraid to organize and join a union because of the potentially hostile reaction from management. She emphasizes the development of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union during her time in various garment shops, noting the union's cocern over working conditions and lack of job security.
    Heltzer recalls joining a dramatic club where she met her husband, emphasizing her and her husband's involvement with plays and the club's choral group. She recalls that her husband worked as a watchmaker but also had other business ventures. Heltzer describes moving to Shelton, Connecticut during World War I and later to Worcester, Massachusetts as her husband changed jobs. She explains that he invested in cotton goods and lost nearly all of this money in a failed business venture in Worcester, prompting the family to move back to New York City. She describes working as a machine operator for the Works Progress Administration (WPA) through which she joined the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU) and the Workers' Unemployed Union (WUU), established in New York City by the Socialist Party of America. She recalls moving through various neighborhoods in New York City in order to find better employment and living conditions, focusing on her time working in her husband's jewelry store on 41st Street and 10th Avenue. She explains that a robbery in the store affected her husband's physical and mental health, prompting her to work at the store by herself for two years before closing it. She emphasizes her family's involvement in and bonding through the Socialist Party, noting that her children grew up around party events due to her and her husband's labor union and other party activities.
    Other topics include a nursing course Heltzer took at Beth Israel Hospital; her children's education and occupations; a comparison of her experiences as a single woman during the 1908 depression and with a family during the Great Depression; the ethnic demographics of the different national and religious groups of the neighborhoods in which she lived and the shops in which she worked; and her work as an unlicensed private nurse until 1965.
    Women socialists |z New York (State) |z New York.
  - Henning, Astrid, 1975 May 7; 593242 (Box 96, Reel 903a - 903d, Box 97, Reel 903e - 903g, Box 1, Folder 41)
    Astrid Henning was born in Norway. She had six siblings and three step-siblings. Her father was a mining engineer and her mother was a nurse. In Norway, she worked as a filing clerk and a packer in a sardine factory. She immigrated to the United States (US) in 1929, where she worked as a domestic worker and an advertiser for a Norwegian newspaper. She married in 1930 and had two children. Her husband was born in Norway and immigrated to the US. He worked as a steward on a yacht and as a clerk in a delicatessen.
    This interview was conducted by Karen Kearns on May 7, 1975. The location is unknown. The interview covers Astrid Henning's working life in Norway and the United States (US) and her family. Henning discusses her family in Norway, including her parents' occupations; her siblings; and her step-siblings. She discusses her first job in Norway as a packer in a sardine factory; her decision to take the job because the wages would enable her immigration to the US; the fact that the men in the factory were unionized but that the women were not; and the fact that her salary enabled her to travel to the US in comfort. She describes her reasons for wanting to immigrate to the US, including the number of children in her family and her desire to travel. She discusses the women with whom she immigrated and the fact that they knew they would work in domestic service in the US, despite coming from middle-class backgrounds.
    Henning discusses her jobs as a domestic worker in Manhasset, New York; Baltimore, Maryland; and New Rochelle, New York. She describes her responsibilities and hours; her feelings of isolation on Long Island; and her employers, including their behavior, their homes, and parties they would host. She explains that she was not responsible for heavy cleaning in any of her positions and that her responsibilities consisted mainly of dusting, dishwashing, and serving. She describes the staff in the different houses in which she worked, including the responsibilities of each staff member; the types of people that were successful in domestic service; and advice she received from co-workers. She compares the behavior of different ethnic groups in domestic service and her disapproval of the Irish workers, who would swear while on duty and play cards late at night. She describes the food that was provided for the staff at different houses in which she worked, including one in which the staff was provided only with leftovers until Henning complained. She recounts being repeatedly subjected to sexual harassment by male employers and warning the men that she would quit if the behavior continued. She describes the experiences of her sister and other women who were sexually harassed and assaulted while in domestic service and their fear of losing their jobs if they reported these incidents. She later recounts sexual harassment in movie theaters and on the subway in New York City; her fear of being alone in public because of these incidents; and the contrast between public behavior in the US and Norway.
    Other topics include meeting her husband while at her first job on Long Island and their courtship; work experiences of her sister and cousin in domestic service and their employers, who included Hattie Carnegie and David O. Selznick; her inability to save money while working in the US; her frustration with people who would not learn the correct pronunciation of her first name; and her work selling advertisements for a Norwegian newspaper in the US.
    Norwegians |z United States |v Interviews.; Women household employees |x Abuse of.; Sexual harassment of women |z New York (State) |z New York.
  - Herzog, Anna, 1975 March 13; 344093
    Anna Herzog was born in 1897 near Minsk, Russia to a Jewish family. Her father died when she was three years old and her older brother supported the family. She and her sister immigrated to the United States (US) in 1910 and settled in New York, New York. She married in 1918, and had her first child in 1930. Herzog worked as a finisher in the garment industry until 1930. She was a member of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.
    This interview was conducted by John Jentz at the Workmen's Circle Home for the Aged in the Bronx, New York on March 13, 1975. The interview covers Anna Herzog's life in Minsk, Russia, her immigration to the United States (US), her involvement in union activities and strikes, and her personal life. Herzog recollects her early life in Minsk, including her father dying when she was three years old; her brother serving as a father figure; Jewish children not being allowed to attend school; wanting to play instead of work; and working for a year in a garment factory on a pedal sewing machine. Her first memories of New York, New York include learning English through friends, and being overwhelmed with the size of New York City. She remembers needing to supply her own sewing machine at her first job; and requiring assistance carrying the sewing machine up and down the stairs. She recalls the differences between garment work in Russia and the United States. She recalls a strike in 1911, during which the workers went on strike for 15 days in order to achieve better pay, better working conditions, and for owner-supplied sewing machines. Herzog's discussion of her personal life includes meeting her husband and their wedding in Toronto, Canada; having two sons and adopting her sister's daughter; discontinuing work because she was pregnant; and moving to the Workmen's Circle Home against her son's wishes.
  - Herzog, Jacob, 1973 April 5; 591902
    Jacob Herzog was born in Austrian Galicia to a large Jewish family. In Galicia he worked as a tinsmith and belonged to an unspecified metalworkers' union. He immigrated to the United States (US) around 1911, where he worked and lived in New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, and Ohio. He worked as a metalworker and was a member of an unspecified building trades union. He married and had two sons.
    This interview was conducted at Jacob Herzog's home on Amsterdam Avenue in Manhattan, New York on April 5, 1973. The interviewer is unknown. Main topics include Herzog's life in Austrian Galicia; his education in the United States (US); and his leisure activities, politics, and union activities. Herzog discusses his life in Galicia, including working as a tinsmith with his father; belonging to an unspecified metalworkers' union; and his father warning him not to join the Army. He recalls learning English in the US through a librarian who would give him books in both Yiddish and English; and attending night school. He discusses leisure activities in which he participated, including going with his children to the park, beach, and baseball games in Brooklyn, New York; having season tickets to the Metropolitan Opera for 35 years; and enjoying attending symphony concerts. Herzog recalls knowing very little about politics upon his arrival to the US; quickly coming to dislike the Republican Party because they represented the rich; and being a member of the Socialist Party of America for most of his life. He discusses his involvement with an unspecified building trades union; his election as a trustee for his New York local; his service on the examining board; and his belief that every worker should be a member of a union.
    Socialists |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Jewish socialists -- New York (State) -- New York -- Interviews.
  - Higgins, John, 1974 May; 344094 (Box 24, Reel 86a)
    John Higgins was born in New Ross, County Wexford, Ireland in 1887 to a large Catholic family. He immigrated to Australia in 1908 and then to the United States in 1910. He married in 1922 and had two children, both of whom died in childhood. He was employed primarily as an engineer and laborer and was a member of International Union of Operating Engineers Local 30.
    This interview was conducted by David Rosenberg in May 1974 at an unknown location. This interview covers Higgins' childhood in Ireland; work experiences in New York, New York; social activities in the Irish community of New York; and his union involvement. Higgins discusses his early life in Ireland, including having a happy childhood; his family owning a small grocery store in New Ross; attending a Christian Brothers school; horseback riding and swimming in a local river before work; working as an accountant for an import/export company in County Wexford; and emigrating from Ireland because he was curious and wanted adventure. He discusses his early experiences in New York, including having no friends or family nearby and living in a community that included Hungarians, Irish, and Germans. His early work experience includes being employed by the Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company until he quit because his pay was less than the other employees'. Higgins discusses stealing a hammer, chisel, and wrench in order to work as a mechanic at a shipyard; working as a carpenter in order to make money while on strike at the shipyard; and making good money at the shipyard because he was willing to work long hours and overtime. He recollects being the chief engineer for multiple hotels, including the St. Andrews Hotel in Manhattan for over 22 years; never having problems finding work because other Irish immigrants would always help him; and belonging to the International Union of Operating Engineers Local 30. He recalls drinking at the pub with his friends; having negative feelings about Prohibition; watching Irish football and hurling on Long Island on Sundays; and being a member and secretary of the County Wexford Organization, which met on 59th Street in Manhattan.
    John Higgins' sister, Katherine Higgins, was also interviewed for the New York City Immigrant Labor Project. See also: Higgins, Katherine.
  - Higgins, Katherine, 1974 April 24; 344095 (Box 24, Reel 87a - 87c)
    Katherine Higgins was born into a large Catholic family in New Ross, County Wexford, Ireland in the 1880s. She lived in England and France before she immigrated to the United States (US) in 1933. She worked for the British War Office during World War I, in the United States Army Quartermaster Corps in France after World War I, and as a lady's companion after her immigration in 1933.
    This interview was conducted by Karen Kearns on April 24, 1974 at an unknown location. This interview covers Katherine Higgins' early life in Ireland, England, and France; her work during and after World War I (WWI); her world travels; and her religion. Higgins discusses her childhood in Ireland in great detail, including the lives of her eight siblings; inheritance laws and her father's disinheritance due to his choice of wife; and Higgins' family home in New Ross. Higgins remembers class distinctions within her community; the education system in Ireland; and her opinion that her life would have been boring had she attended college. She recalls living in England, where she studied to be a teacher and worked for the British War Office during WWI. She discusses the 1916 Easter Rising and its aftermath, including her brother-in-law's wrongful incarceration for weapons possession; the hunger strike and eventual death of Terence MacSwiney; and the fact that her family supported the revolution but believed that it occurred too late. She discusses her work with the United States Army Quartermaster Corps in France after WWI, designing cemeteries for the reburial of American soldiers, and organizing a chapter of American Gold Star Mothers. She explains that she immigrated to the United States (US) and settled in New York, New York in 1933 because it was the only place she could find work. Her first impressions of the US include her surprise at the bigotry towards the Irish and her amazement at the poor education of American men. Higgins discusses her work as a lady's companion, including attending the film premiere of Gone with the Wind; visiting some of the Nordic countries, the Baltics, and the Soviet Union; and enjoying the fact that her employer owned a car. She also discusses her religious influences, practices, and ideologies, including the fact that she did not practice Catholicism in the years between leaving Ireland and arriving in the US; her opinion that the French were not devout Catholics; that she attended St. Patrick's Cathedral in Manhattan; and the Irish fear of the afterlife.
    Higgins' brother, John Higgins, was also interviewed for the New York City Immigrant Labor Project. See also: Higgins, John.
    Women household employees |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.
  - Hochberg, Eddie, 1975 March 3; 344096 (Box 24, Reel 88a, Box 25, Reel 88a - 88b, Box 100, Cassette 88a - 88b)
    Eddie Hochberg was born in Russia to a Jewish family. He immigrated to the United States in 1914, where he was employed in the garment industry. He was a member of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union Local 22, the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, and the United Brotherhood of Cloak Makers Local 1.
    This interview was conducted at the Workmen's Circle Home for the Aged in the Bronx, New York on March 3, 1975 by David Lightner. The main topics include Eddie Hochberg's life in Russia; his immigration to the United States (US); his work in the garment industry both in Russia and the US; and the internal organization of garment workers' labor unions in New York, New York. Hochberg discusses his early life in Russia, including his family's poverty and his father's work as a supervisor in a logging company. He discusses the immigration of his family to the US, including his father immigrating in 1911 and finding work in a paper box factory; two of his brothers immigrating after their father; Hochberg immigrating alone in 1914; and the rest of his family following in 1916. He describes finding his first job through a man with whom he attended synagogue; not being paid for three weeks while he learned the trade; and his first job turning over coats to create seams. He discusses his movement through different factories within the garment industry and his work in each, including manufacturing coats for men, cloaks, and dresses; being paid for both week work and piecework; cleaning and oiling the machines every Friday; working overtime during the busy season; and having to find other employment during the summer. He describes the introduction of labor unions into the garment industry, including the fact that very few companies were unionized initially; the establishment of the National Recovery Administration in 1933 guaranteeing workers the right to join unions; that different locals within the same international union being determined by profession as well as ethnicity; and unions providing benefits such as better pay, vacations, and pensions. Hochberg also mentions that he was a member of multiple unions, including the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union Local 22, the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, and the United Brotherhood of Cloak Makers Local 1.
  - Hoffman, Simon, 1974 April 4; 593244 (Box 97, Reel 904a - 904b, Box 1, Folder 42)
    Simon Hoffman was born in Pilviskiai, Russia in 1893 to a Jewish family. His father worked as a butcher and his mother worked as a wig maker. Hoffman immigrated to the United States (US) through Ellis Island in New York, New York in 1913. He briefly lived with his step-siblings in the Bronx before finding a job as a cap maker. During the Great Depression, Hoffman was employed by the City of New York cleaning public parks. He became a US citizen and a member of the Democratic Party in 1920. He continued to work in the cap making industry until his retirement. He was a member of an unspecified cap makers' union (likely the United Hatters of North America).